Guide to the Atterbury Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Atterbury papers
1654-1757
OSB MSS 26
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
The papers include correspondence and legal documents relating to the careers of Lewis Atterbury (d. 1693), Lewis Atterbury (1656-1731), and Francis Atterbury, as well as various receipts, epitaphs, poems, prayers, and seals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Francis and Lewis Atterbury.
Clergy -- Great Britain; Atterbury, Francis, 1662-1732; Atterbury, Lewis, 1656-1731; Atterbury, Lewis, -1693; Gibson, Edmund, 1669-1748; Church of England ( Benefices)
- Correspondence
  - Atterbury, Francis, Bp. of Rochester, 1662-1732
    - ALS to Lewis Atterbury, [London], 1693 Oct (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Reports to his father his election as preacher of Bridewell Hospital.
    - 2 ALS to Lewis Atterbury, [n.p.], [1721] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Discusses their correct ages, and reports on his gout and his wife's illness.
  - [Atterbury, Lewis], d. 1693. Documents concerning the clerical career of Lewis Atterbury, 1654 May 24-1689 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Papers of approbation, ordination, institution, subscription, and certification. 11 items.
  - [Atterbury, Lewis], 1656-1731. Documents relating to the clerical career of Lewis Atterbury, 1679 Sep 21- 1719 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Papers of ordination, institution, certification and preferment. 23 items.
  - Busby, Richard, 1606-1695. ALS to Lewis Atterbury, [n.p.], [ca. 1680] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Concerns the rebuilding of Willen Parich Church.
  - Clagett, Nicholas, Bp. of Exeter, d. 1746. ALS to Lowde Banks, [n.p.], 1726 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    On the Queen's bounty.
  - Delafaye, Charles, b. 1678? 2 ALS to Lewis Atterbury, Whitehall, 1707 Aug 18, 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Concerns efforts by Atterbury to receive patent for presentation of Rectory of Shepperton. Accompanied by listing of fees paid for passing of patent.
  - Edwards, Samuel D'Elboeuf. Document, listing fees paid for Presentation to Mainston Rectory, 1757 Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Mainston Rectory, County Salop, was the gift of the Lord Keeper, Sir Robert Henley.
  - Gibson, Edmund, Bp. of London, 1669-1748. ALS to Lewis Atterbury, Lambeth, 1707 Jul 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    About Atterbury's translation of Reunion of Christians. Gibson encouraged publication, but ...
  - Guilford, Francis North, 1st Baron, 1637-1685. Document, signed, concerning Lewis Atterbury, 1684 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Allows Atterbury to officiate in the Chapel Royal of Holy and Undivided Trinity.
  - Henry, Duke of Gloucester, 1639-1660. Document, signed, concerning Lewis Atterbury, Whitehall, 1660 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Appoints Atterbury his Chaplain Extraordinary.
  - Nottingham, Daniel Finch, 2d Earl of, 1647-1730. 2 ALS to Lewis Atterbury, [n.p.], 1677 Sep 1, 1685 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    On Atterbury's offer to oversee workmen and restoration at Milton.
  - Pritchard, Sir William, 1632?-1705. Document, signed, concerning Lewis Atterbury, [London], 1683 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Recommends Atterbury, who had served him as chaplain during his term as Lord Mayor of London, for ecclesiastical preferment.
  - Sexham, Ernald de. Document (copy) concerning institution of Ernald de Sexham to the Rectory Church of St. Andrew in Sexham County in 1206, [1757] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Institution took place on 6th October 1206, during the reign of King John.
  - Tillotson, John, Abp. of Canterbury, 1630-1694. ALS to Lewis Atterbury, 1685 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Asks Atterbury to preach for him at Lincoln's Inn.
  - Townshend, John. Articles of Agreement for payment of rent, 1704 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Thomas Drewe agrees to pay rent to John Townshend, citizen and ropemaker of London.
  - Trevor, Richard, Bp. of Durham, 1707-1771. Calls for Convocation, (2 documents, signed), 1743 Mar 1, 1747 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Calls for Convocation issued while Trevor was Bishop of St. David's. Accompanied by similar call issued on 1754 Mar 2 by Anthony Ellys.
  - Wake, William, Abp. of Canterbury, 1657-1737. ALS to Lewis Atterbury, 1708 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Introduces a clergyman, John Smith, and asks Atterbury to help him.
  - Willis, Thomas, d. 1692. ALS to Lewis Atterbury, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Manuscripts, 1662-1754, n.d.
  - Autographs, 1662-1754, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1704-05 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Epitaph, "To a Greyhound", [18th century] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    "To the memory of Signor Fido, an Italian of good extraction who cam into England not to bite us.. ."
  - "The Lady's Scull," manuscript poem., [18th century] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Suggested by two carved pedestals with a man and woman's skull on top, in alcove called "Il Penseroso" in Tyler's Garden at Denbigh, Surrey.
  - Prayers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Anonymous manuscript, 3 items
  - Terrick, Richard, Bp. of London, 1710-1777. [Livings in the patronage of the Bishop of London], [ca. 1770] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Anonymous manuscript. 3 items.
  - [Wheat prices of wheat from 1270 to 1594], [18th century] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Anonymous manuscript.